Have you ever wondered how much faster a
top level World Cup rider actually is?
Well, I have wondered quite a lot
actually. I've been filming the mountain
bike World [music] Cups for a few years
now and I've seen this guy pass me at
warp speed and I always wondered, how is
this possible that they go so goddamn
fast? So, I did try to figure out
[music] how much faster these guys
actually were by starting a series
average rider versus World Cup rider,
which started with Amaury Pierron, the
winner of the first round of the UCI
downhill World Cup in South Korea and
followed by an episode with Loris
Vergier
>> [music]
>> who is unfortunately injured. But, those
first two episodes had a slight flaw.
They weren't filmed on a World Cup
track. They were filmed sure, on a hard
track, but I reckon the difference would
be even bigger if they were made on a
hard, tough World Cup track. So, to
rectify this, I drove to Andorra to race
with the current goat of mountain
biking. So, as usual, I've rented a
downhill bike because what fun would it
be to ride a bike that I actually knew
versus the best downhill rider on the
planet. But, wait.
What am I hearing? Is it a bird?
Is it a plane? No, I think it's
>> [music]
[music]
>> All right, so as you've probably
guessed, I am here today with Loïc
Bruni. Loïc, how you doing? Pretty good,
thank you. Good. Okay, so we're in
Andorra. Loïc is cheating a little bit
because it's his home track. But, we've
got a bit of a trial run this morning
and the difference is
staggering. Let's put it that way. Come
on. Uh
it is quite big. Yeah, but for your
defense, the tracks you did before were
a little bit easier, flowier than this
one. I do agree. That's why I wanted to
try with you on a track that's actually
harder. So, I think the harder the track
gets, the bigger the gap with the
average guy, really. Yeah, and and put
it affectively, this is a World Cup
track. It is a World Cup track.
>> we raced two or three years ago. Yeah,
it was done
>> So, it's not like just a bike park
track. I know at the start of your
career, you were being consistent. I
know there was a lot of crashes and uh
you weren't sure you the pace was there,
but you you wouldn't win because you'd
crash a lot. How did you get to that
point of being, you know,
super consistent, but, as we're going to
see pretty soon, super fast.
>> It's what I
did the
the realization myself, too. I was like,
I cannot be consistent. I was a little
bit struggling with finishing or even
racing the whole season.
Uh with injuries and stuff. So, I had to
find a way mentally to
put myself down and then have a bit more
like smaller peaks through my uh my
season.
And uh it's difficult because I had to
change who I
or how I approach things and stuff, but
uh with the right surroundings, I found
a way to be a little bit more consistent
and try to have
a better day on the days where I felt
really bad or felt like it was not for
me. And I worked a lot on my weaknesses
and I tried to be smarter, mainly, and
use my experience, which is only
getting you more and more useful now
because the young guys are coming with
an insane amount of talent and speed.
What do What do was the main two things
that you changed from the old Loic when
you used to crash a lot and not win and
the new Loic?
I think it was it had a lot to do with
the look and the judgement from other
people.
You know, like the
It could be from random journalists,
photographs telling me oh you look so
fast today or whatever or even random
people on Instagram or Pinkbike
comments. Do you read things that you go
through and you read Pinkbike comments?
>> I stopped. I stopped People stopped
being mean on the internet. Yeah, now
that most people are fine. It's just
like one comment that hits you
personally and and that's a little bit
more difficult to swallow because you're
like
What are you What Why is this guy saying
this, you know, like and we are just
humans. So when you're a human and you
see something negative about you you it
hits you and you think about it and then
I was just like way too
vulnerable to these kind of things.
And I would just my That's why my
confidence would go like this and my
commitment too and it would be like just
a big blur of things and then I started
to cut
away these comments and these things so
I could protect myself and just do my
own thing and I think that's when I
started to
do what I
had to and what I knew what to do.
Going back to the topic at hand being
you know, average rider versus pro
rider.
Do you ever ride with normal people?
To be honest, no. No, no, no because in
testing we are usually alone or with the
team people like it's pretty closed.
Yeah. And when I ride downhill maybe in
summer some people want to ride with me
but they are already like fast guys.
Because random guys that don't ride a
lot they don't dare to say hey can I
ride with you? It's like a bit
the gap is big for them so
I don't really do but you ride you're
not that average cuz you ride quite a
lot. I would say.
>> ride quite a lot. I I would say on the
higher end of the average. Yeah. would
Average plus and I think you're you're
really good. The only thing is
when you do a full run like this against
people like me whose it is the job to do
that, it's difficult just physically to
hold on the your intensity all the way
down, you know? How many times a week do
you go to the gym?
Three times. Yeah. Last time I went to
the gym was in 2010, I believe.
Loic gets down the track in 3 minutes
40. We've timed it this morning. How
long do you think you can give me
and catch me and catch me or not before
the end? How long do you want?
Like like 3 minutes 40?
>> [laughter]
>> I reckon you gave in the past to run on
an ASA.
>> Yes, I give them 23%
percent
of time, but I reckon you could do
better than that cuz it's a World Cup
track and it's long. Yeah.
So, if you want we can give you a
minute. Yeah. That's a proper a proper
margin to play with.
That is so demoralizing. So, that guy's
going to start a minute after me. He
feels confident he can actually catch
me. I'm like After Loic towed me on some
of the big jumps to make sure I could
clear them, we then agreed on a race
line for us both. Then we got to work.
Yo!
The first section is really fast and
leads to nasty rock garden which Loic
flies over. As he gets in way quicker
than me, it allows him to jump into the
flat section of the rock garden then
jump out of it lining him up perfectly
for the jump and only touching the
ground once. You can see here that I'm
getting bucked by all those rocks and
lose a ton of speed trying to keep the
high line in order to line up for the
next section. On GoPro, the difference
is even more staggering. While he barely
touches the brakes and jumps into key
sections, I freak out and slow down,
which doesn't allow me to skim over the
rocks like he does. And that's 4 seconds
in the bank for Loic Bruni on the first
four corners.
I'm no expert, but I'm pretty sure this
section alone was at least 5 seconds.
Section two is roots galore, but it
doesn't really affect Bruni as he
doesn't bloody touch them much, gapping
a whole section.
We actually start pretty similarly on
this section, but while I brake to not
get bucked by the massive root up top,
he accelerate in order to gap the entire
section. Once that's done, it's
basically game over. I've lost a ton of
speed in the rough section, while he's
gained many seconds skipping it and
accelerating on landing.
On this section, we actually get to a
point where Loic is 50% faster than me.
That means he's running at 1.5 times my
speed. I'm not even sure how his eyes
are keeping up. Might just be pure
muscle memory at this stage.
Getting these pro riders to work for our
video.
Can't have the easy life all the time.
How did this feel to walk up the track,
Loic?
Section three is a nasty rock garden
finishing on a root garden that for some
of us can be gapped.
Oh,
On the first rock garden section, Loic
isn't afraid to keep the high line and
skim the tree, keeping him away from the
roughest parts. He then proceeds to jump
the whole root section, while I have to
brake in order to not get bucked off the
first root as it gets steep and rough
behind. This jump alone is probably
worth a couple of seconds.
The most impressive part is that he
doesn't really brake for anything that's
not necessary. He will pull on the lever
only if there is an absolute need to
slow down, but at no point braking
happens because he isn't in control or
doesn't know what to do. All right,
Loic. All right. So, this is it. We've
done the track a couple times. I've
managed to pick some of the line you're
taking, which I was doing wrong, so I'm
going to use some of that. Do you reckon
you can catch me in a if I if you leave
me 1 minute, knowing that the track is
about 3:40, give or take? Um it's going
to be tough because I think with the
laps you're getting a bit faster and
faster and me not because it was like I
know this track already.
>> fast. Yeah. But uh let's give it a
minute and see if I can catch you. Yeah,
1 minute. Okay. Also,
no pedaling. Okay. You can
>> get three pedal strokes here.
>> And you? What about you?
>> I saw I saw you the other day. No, no
pedaling for me either. Maybe I'll
cheat, but I saw you like just there.
You like putting cranks in. I was like,
"Fuck, how am I supposed to compete with
a guy that's putting cranks in the
middle of his run?" But no pedaling.
Okay, no pedaling.
>> All right.
Um
Charlie in the gate. 5 4 3 2 1. Go for
it. Come on.
Okay, stop pedaling.
All right. First thing I got to say is
Bernie here in power and cylinder. What
track you guys riding?
DH.
Oh, yeah. Yeah.
It's good.
What's the best riding? That one is the
best.
After filming him and watching him ride,
I knew there's going to be some sections
that are going to be very tough for me.
However, it's given me some lines. I've
done a few laps and
I mean
I'm relatively good form.
Okay, 30 seconds in. Half of the gap is
happening.
I had I had time to make some friends.
Ah,
still rental bikes as a you know, I do
this just kind of what I do.
But
he just gets into stuff way quicker than
me.
Also,
well, like lives here, so this he's
cheating a little bit. Ah. Charlie's
probably on the long of camber by now.
I have a stressed day. Ah, just
I don't So, he knows the track. Ah. like
the bottom of it
and we're up to high nine there.
Okay,
I wonder what he thinks up there
is
maybe I've left it too much time but
he's a confident man. He's won
four
I believe or
a good champion chips
a good bunch of world champions as well.
A 55 put in the pocket Charlie I'm I'm
coming.
Okay, five, four, three,
two, one,
let's go.
I'm flying up can't see anything.
Got a bit loose there.
There's a 23% difference between me and
Ace and Ronan but I think on the world
cup track it might be boy
that jump is huge. I'm not used to jump
stuff that big.
Okay,
we're in there.
Oh, that's the wrong line. Losing the
rear.
Okay.
Still on.
Charlie, I'm coming.
Charlie, I actually did those sick
jumps.
>> Look at that.
Some power attracted before. Well, I
can't be so helpful like that. Oh.
Our brakes are fading.
Especially the rear, that's not good. At
all.
Okay.
Don't know which lane
he's going to take here.
Oh, I got to pop the brake.
Okay. Okay.
We said no pedaling.
Pedaling. You give me a line, good then.
I just be patient. Come on. Come on.
No pedaling. No pedaling.
I'm respecting the rules. That's kind of
unlike me.
Okay, no pedal. My leg starts to burn
already.
All right. Okay.
Straight jump into this.
I can't hear him, so
we're still good.
Okay. Okay.
Oh, bloody hell, I still got this.
Come on.
Okay.
A high line, I think he took there. A
good job there.
Okay.
I still can't hear him.
Wonder what strategy is.
Woah.
Okay.
Oh my god, my hands [music] and my arms
are starting to tire pretty bad.
It's been about
I would say 15 [music] years since I've
stepped foot into a gym.
And look what he does every week.
This is like the section where he's
going to put
so much time into me. I know that
already.
He's just got here which
is absolutely
bonkers.
Nice.
I can still not see any dust.
Which is worrying.
I'm losing.
I'm losing strength.
Oh,
God, my
everything
This walker track is just a different
from a normal track. It's
demanding. It's so quick.
Oh, I can see someone.
Perfect.
He's picked up some speed
for sure.
Oh my god.
My wrist
really
bloody hurts. Oh, there's someone
yelling behind me. Maybe it's Bernie,
maybe it's not. It's a public track. I
really hope it's not him.
Oh,
is it going to be hard for me to pass
him FROM NOW ON?
THE BOY DID NOT MUCK AROUND.
>> [panting]
>> There wasn't much space for a pass, and
yet maybe watch out 10 dogs in because
I like Bernie.
I am at 2027. Maybe that's a thing.
Oh god, this is a sketchy section.
My arms are absolutely
choice.
I managed to cook myself,
that's for sure.
I hide again.
No.
Not too bad, hey? Oh, not too bad. Not
too bad.
Holy crap, that's That was hard.
There's so many fast guys here. All the
fast guys are here.
>> [laughter]